Mss.B.M891
American Philosophical Society
- Correspondence, 0.25 ln. ft. 36 items; 1 upright box, 10 oversize items.; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815; Muhlenberg, John Peter Gabriel, 1746-1807; Muhlenberg, Peter Gabriel
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Presented by Rev. Frederick A. Muhlenberg, 1891, and Mrs. Jesse Wagner, 1952; accessioned, 1952 (1952 89901). See in-house shelf list for additional accession information.
  Botany; Foreign Language; Herbaria.; Natural History; Religion
  - Certificate of membership to Heinrich Mühlenberg, Dec. 26, 1774; 8-1/2x8-3/4; German Society of Pennsylvania.
    Scope and Contents note
    Philadelphia, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Michael Shubart, Sec. 1p. In German. Seal. parchment. (see Mühlenberg family papers.) Removed from frame February 1963.
  - Diploma to Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg, Oct. 1, 1769; Oversize box; 19x15; Halle. Universität
    Halle, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Fred. Christ. Juncker. 1p. In Latin. Seal. Removed to resotre April 1972, W. Spawn.
  - Membership certificate in the Society of Cincinnati for Muhlenberg, October 31, 1785, 1785 October 31; 1.0 Item(s); Vellum certificate of membership.; D.S: 1p. Parchment (signature faded).; Society of the Cincinnati.
    General note
    FILM 371 FRAME 11
    Signed by Geo. Washington, president. Removed for exhibit 18 July 1980 in Germany, returned 16 December 1981.
    Muhlenberg, John Peter Gabriel, 1746-1807
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], June 7, 1798; 9-3/4x8; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth, A.L.S. 2p. In German with Latin scientific names. Botanical matters. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], June 18, 1798; 10x7-3/4; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth, A.L.S. 2p. In German with Latin scientific names. Includes list of botanical books. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Certificate of membership to Heinrich Mühlenberg, July 20, 1798; Oversize box; 14x15-3/4; Naturforschende Gesellschaft Westphalens
    D.on printed form. 1p. In German. Seal. Given to Muhlenberg when he was principal of Franklin College and minister of Trinity Church. (see Mühlenberg family papers.) Removed from frame February 1963. Removed to restore 1 May 1972 (W. Spawn), returned 21 May 1972.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], July 23, 1798; 10x8; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth, A.L.S. 3p.and end. In German with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 1-43, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], October 19, 1798; 10x8; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 2p.,end. In German with Latin names. List of plants, nos. 44-60, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], October 20, 1798; 10x7-3/4; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth, A.L.S. 2p. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 80-117, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], November 1, 1798; 9x7-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 4p. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 26-79; 118-141, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], December 10, 1798; 10x7-3/4; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth Hall, A.L.S. 2p. and end. In German, with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 142-163, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], December 23, 1798; 9x7-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth Hall, A.L.S. 2p. German text and Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 164-187, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], December 30, 1798; 9x7-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth Hall, A.L.S. 2p. German text and Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 188-206 inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to H[einrich Ernst] Mühlenberg, January 9, 1799; 9x8; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 207-229 inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], January 31, 1799; 8x6-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants. nos. 188-197; 230-250, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], February 4, 1799; 8x6-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. German text with Latin names. List of plants, nos. 207-227; 251-271, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], February 20, 1799; 8x6-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. German text, with Latin scientific names. Lists plants, nos. 272-313, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], May 24, 1799; 8x7; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 2p. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 338-353. inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], July 1, 1799; 8x6-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth Hall, A.L.S. 2p. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 370-391 inclusive. Mentions Dr. Horsfield. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], August 10, 1799; 8x7; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Nazareth Hall, A.L.S. 2p.and end. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos. 392-406 inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], September 17, 1799; 10x8; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Bethlehem, A.L.S. 3p.and end. German text with Latin scientific names. List of plants, nos.407-422, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Letter to [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg], September 28, 1799; 8x6-3/4; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    A.L.S. 2p.and end. German text and Latin scientific names. Mentions Gustav von Dalmann. List of plants, nos. 423-441, inclusive. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Certificate of membership to Henricum Mühlenberg., March 10, 1802; Oversize box; 11x13-3/4; Societas Physica Gottingensis
    D. 1p. Seal. In Latin. Removed from frame February 1963.
  - Commission to Peter Muhlenberg as 1st Lieut., February 23, 1809; Oversize box; 18 1/4" x 15 1/4"; United States. President (1801-1809: Jefferson)
    In the 6th regiment of infantry Washington, D.S: Th. Jefferson 1p. Parchment Seal Removed to restore 5 March 1952 (W. Spawn), returned 13 March 1952.
  - Henry Muhlenberg, membership certificate in Linnean Society of Philadelphia, 1809., 1.0 Item(s) Oversize box; Membership certificate.; 13-1/2x16-3/4; Philadelphia, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.; Linnean Society of Philadelphia.
    Signed by Benjamin Smith Barton, Pres.,et al. 1p. In Latin. (see Mühlenberg family papers.) Removed from frame February 1963.
    Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
  - Commission to Peter Muhlenberg as Captain in the 6th regiment of Infantry, May 1, 1811; Oversize box; 17 1/2" x 14"; United States. President (1809-1817: Madison)
    FILM 321 FRAME 16
    Washington, D.S.: James Madison 1p. Parchment Seal. Removed to restore 5 March 1952 (W. Spawn), returned 13 March 1952.
  - Letter to Henry [Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst] Mülenberg, Fairfield, River Thames, October 4, 1811; 12x7-1/2; Denke, Christian Frederick, 1775-1838
    Lancaster. A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. In German. Botanical matters. Film 403 Frame 22. Originally B.M89.d.
  - Certificate of membership as corresponding member, to Henry Mühlenbergh [xic], Sept. 1, 1814; 9-1/2x8; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
    Philadelphia, Sept. Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: Reuben Haines. 1p. (see Mühlenberg family papers.) Removed from frame February 1963.
  - Commission to Peter Muhlenberg as Major in the 31st regiment of infantry, Feb. 1, 1815; Oversize box; 18 1/2" x 15"; United States. President (1809-1817: Madison)
    FILM 370 FRAME 11
    Washington, D.S: James Madison 1p. Parchment Seal. Removed to restore 5 March 1952 (W. Spawn), returned 13 March 1952.
  - Certificate of membership, to Henry Mühlenberg, Lancaster, Penna., March 8, 1815; 8-1/4x6-1/2; Societas Physiographica Lundensis
    Lund, Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: C. A. Agardh and one other. In Latin. 1p.and add.,end. (see Mühlenberg family papers.) Removed from frame February 1963.
  - Commission to Peter Muhlenberg as paymaster, March 5, 1835; Oversize box; 18" x 13 3/4"; United States. President (1829-1837: Jackson)
    Washington, D.S: Andrew Jackson 1p. Parchment Seal (see Muhlenberg family papers). Removed to restore 5 March 1952 (W. Spawn), returned 13 March 1952.
  - Letter to Jno. Ritter, Dec. 3, 1844; 9 1/2" x 7 1/2"; Muhlenberg, Henry Augustus Philip, 1782-1844
    Reading, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. (see Muhlenberg family papers). FILM 371 FRAME 11
  - Commission to Frank P. Muhlenberg as 1st Lieut. in the 13th regiment of infantry, Aug. 17, 1861; Oversize box; 17 1/2" x 13 3/4"; United States. President (1861-1865: Lincoln)
    Washington, D.S.: Abraham Lincoln 1p. Parchment Seal ----Copy. Removed to restore 5 March 1952 (W. Spawn), returned 13 March 1952.
  - Letter to Capt. F.P. Muhlenberg, April 24, 1865; 9 3/4" x 7 3/4"; United States. Army
    Albany, L. 2p. (see Muhlenberg family papers) Special order No. 4 pertaining to the guard of honor near the body of Abraham Lincoln while it remained in Albany. FILM 371 FRAME 4
  - Letter to Capt. F.P. Muhlenberg, April 25, 1865; 7 3/4" x 5"; U.S. Committee of Arrangement for Funeral of Abraham Lincoln.
    Albany, L. 1p. (see Muhlenberg family papers). FILM 371 FRAME 11
  - Commission to Frank P. Muhlenberg as Brevet Major in the U.S. Army, Aug. 10, 1866; Oversize box; 18 3/4" x 15 1/2"; United States. President (1865-1869: Johnson)
    Washington, D.S: Andrew Johnson 1p. Parchment Seal. Removed to restore 5 March 1952 (W. Spawn), returned 13 March 1952.
- Bound Volumes, 24.0 Volume(s); Henry Muhlenberg Journals (volumes 16 and 17): A record of daily occurrence, with many features of a commonplace book, for this contains prescriptions, notes of questions asked candidates for the Lutheran ministry, the plan of a barn, etc. There is also a biographical account of Rev. Henry Melchior Muhlenberg (1711-1787). Botanical notebooks (all other volumes): Written in Latin or German script, and in a small hand, this great mass of materials, probably of considerable significance, has seldom been used and never entirely studied with care. Letterbook: Written in English by Peter Gabriel Muhlenberg, in his role as paymaster of the U.S. Army.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815; Muhlenberg, Peter Gabriel
  Biographical/Historical note
  Henry Muhlenberg (also known as Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Muhlenberg) was a Lutheran clergyman whose avocation was botany. He was well known on both sides of the Atlantic Ocean for his botanical work. He lived in Lancaster, Pennsylvania, and studied the flora there, keeping several volumes of notes.
  Calendarium florae (volume 8): Presented by Henry Muhlenberg, 1785. Henry Muhlenberg Journals (volumes 16 and 17): Presented by Hiester Muhlenberg, 1954; accessioned, 1956 (1956 1143ms, 1144ms). Other Henry Muhlenberg volumes presented by Rev. Frederick A. Muhlenberg, 1890. Peter Muhlenberg letterbook (volume 25) presented by Mrs. Jesse Wagner, 1952; accessioned, 1952 (1952 89901). See in-house shelf list for additional accession information.
  For some information on the botanical manuscripts and their author, see C. Earle Smith, Jr. "Henry Muhlenberg--Botanical Pioneer," American Philosophical Society Proceedings 106(1962):443-460.
  Muhlenberg, Henry Melchior, 1711-1787; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840; Agriculture -- United States.; Barns.; Botany; Fungi.; Grasses.; Journals (notebooks).; Lancaster (Pa.) -- Description and travel.; Lichens.; Meteorology - Observations; Military Records; Natural history.; Plants.; Shrubs.; Sketches.; Trees.; Zoology -- Vermont.
  - 1. Agrostographia Pensilvanica, 1792., 1.0 Volume(s); Descriptions of the grasses of Pennsylvania.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 584.9 M89.
  - 2. Botanical notebook., undated; 1.0 Volume(s); Descriptions of plants, with some sketches; extracts from published descriptions of oaks, pines, etc.; 1 volume. "Auf einer Reise nach Philadelphia" is bound in the back of the volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89bot.
    - 2a. Auf einer Reise nach Philadelphia., 1810; Bound with volume 2, "Botanical notebook."; 23 leaves (1 msg.), 4" x 6-3/4", with illustrations. Bound with volume 2, "Botanical notebook."; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
      Diary bound at back of botanical notebook.
      - 2b. Plots for gardens (?), undated; 4.0 Item(s) 4 maps, 17.8 x 10.8 cm; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
        The maps in this notebook, part of a large collection of Muhlenberg's writings on botany and natural history, seem to be plots for gardens he maintained.
        Other Finding Aids note
        Realms of Gold, 34 (1).
  - 3. Botanice, 1781., 1.0 Volume(s); Catalog of plants, with special reference to North American species, identified and described according to a disused system of Linnaeus.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Old call number 580 M89b.
  - 4. Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785., 1.0 Volume(s); Journal and daybook, with lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Old call number 580 M89bo.
  - 5. Botanisches Tagebuch, 1786-1790., 1.0 Volume(s); Contents similar to Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785: journal and daybook, lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call numbers 580 M89bo, 580 M89de
  - 6. Botanisches Tagebuch, 1807-1815., 1.0 Volume(s); Contents similar to Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785: journal and daybook, lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
  - 7. Botany, a notebook., undated; 1.0 Volume(s); An early version of the author's Catalog of the Hitherto Known... Plants of North America. In this volume is a catalog of plants found in Burlington and Gloucester Counties, N.J., by C.S. Rafinesque.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89bota.
  - 8. Calendarium florae, 1785., 1.0 Volume(s); Much the same as the previous volume, Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785: journal and daybook, lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Old call number 580 M89c.
  - 9. Catalog of the hitherto known plants in the United States, 1808., 1.0 Volume(s); 1 volume. Bound with this is "Folio plantarum Lancastriensium," 1808. 1 vol., with 222 figures.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Old call number 586 M89ca.
    - 9a. Folio plantarum Lancastriensium, 1808., 1.0 Volume(s) Bound with volume 9, "Catalog of the hitherto known plants in the United States."; Bound with volume 9, "Catalog of the hiterhto known plants in the United States."; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
  - 10. Descriptio plantarum ex aliis partibus Americae septentrionalis, 1792., 1.0 Volume(s); Notes on herbs, shrubs, and trees from North America.; 1 volume. "Botanische beiträge" is bound in the back of the volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call numbers 580 M89c, 580 M89d.
    - 10a. Botanische beiträge zur Landwirt, circa 1792; 1.0 Volume(s) Bound in volume 10, "Descriptio plantarum."; Bound in the back of volume 10, "Descriptio plantarum."; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
      Relating to North American plants.
  - 11. Descriptio uberior graminum et plantarium calamariarum Americae septentionalis indigenarum et cicurum., undated; 1.0 Volume(s); Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Old call number 580 M89de.
  - 12. Flora Lancastriensis: botanisches Tagebuch, 1790-1799., 1.0 Volume(s); Contents similar to Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785: journal and daybook, lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89f.
    This manuscript is later than the published paper of 1785 and could not have been presented by G.H.E. Muhlenberg in 1785. The manuscript is indeed a tagebuch for 1790 and thereafter. - M. Mears(?), 5 June 1981
  - 13. Fortsetzung meines Journals von Botanic und der Naturhistorie, 1799 - 1807., 1.0 Volume(s); Contents similar to Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785: journal and daybook, lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume. List of species, dates appears in the back of the volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89fo.
  - 14. Fungi Pensylvaniae mediae., 1793; 1.0 Volume(s); Fungi observed and described, 1793 and later.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 589.2 M89.
  - 15. Gräser die bei Lancaster wild wachsen., undated; 1.0 Volume(s); Lists of grasses seen in the vicinity of Lancaster or on his travels, such as meadow grasses, white timothy, miller's grass, sedges, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 584.9 M89g.
  - 16-17. Journals of Henry Muhlenberg, 1777-1815., 2.0 Volume(s) 2 volumes, 1100 p.; A record of daily occurrence, with many features of a commonplace book, for this contains prescriptions, notes of questions asked candidates for the Lutheran ministry, the plan of a barn, etc. There is also a biographical account of Rev. Henry Melchior Muhlenberg (1711-1787).; 2 volumes, 1100 p.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
    Henry Muhlenberg (also known as Gotthilf Heinrich Muhlenberg) was a Lutheran clergyman and a botanist.
    Presented by Hiester Muhlenberg, 1954; accessioned, 1956 (1956 1143ms, 1144ms).
    Old call number BM892.
    Muhlenberg, Henry Melchior, 1711-1787; Barns.; Botany; Journals (notebooks).; Lutheran Church -- Clergy.
  - 18. Lichenes Lancastriensis, 1791., 1.0 Volume(s); 1 volume. "Cryptogama Lancastriensia," 1791, is bound in the same volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 586 M89c.
    - 18a. Cryptogama Lancastriensia, 1791., 586 M89c; 1.0 Volume(s) Bound with volume 18, "Lichenes Lancastriensis."; Botanical notes on ferns, mosses, fungi, lichens, etc., especially those found in the vicinity of Lancaster, Pa.; 1 volume. Bound with volume 18, "Lichenes Lancastriensis," 1791.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
  - 19. Monographia plantarum Lancastriensis, 1792., 1.0 Volume(s); Descriptions of trees, shrubs, and plants, including local names in German, English, and Indian languages.; 1 volume. Bound with No. 19 is "Samlungen von dem was ich aus dem Thierreich habe bemerken können," 1 vol. This contains Muhlenberg's observations of animals, birds, and insects in and near Lancaster; and also a list of the native animals of Vermont.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Volume 2; volume 1 (#20) in German. Old call number 580 M89m.
    - 19a. Samlungen von dem was ich aus dem Thierreich habe bemerken können, 1785-1799; Bound with volume 19, Monographia plantarum Lancastriensis."; Bound in the back of volume 19, "Monographia plantarum Lancastriensis."; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
      Includes definitions for Delaware Indian words, said to be taken from the Essay of a Delaware Indian and English Spelling Book 1776.
      Delaware Indians
  - 20. Monographien von Gewächsen aus Lancaster, 1790., 1.0 Volume(s); 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89mo. Volume 2 (#19) in Latin.
  - 21. Natur-tagebuch, 1786., 1.0 Volume(s); Diary for 11 January 20 June, kept irregularly, with descriptions of plants and grasses, record of purchases, medical recipes, comments on weather, etc.; 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89n.
  - 22. Pflanzen die ich noch nicht nach dem Linn, bestimen kann, weitl, uftich zu meinem eignen Verbessern beschrieben im Jahr 1788., 1.0 Volume(s); Descriptions of plants, from herbs and cassia to cryptogamis, which he has seen but plans at a later date to describe more fully.; 1 volume. "Nachschrift von Baümen und Stauden, 1787" is bound in the back of the volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89p.
    - 22a. Nachschrift von Baümen und Stauden, 1787., 1.0 Volume(s) Bound with volume 22, "Pflanzen die ich noch nicht nach dem Linn."; Description of trees and shrubs, including red cedar, dogwood, acacia, pine, which he had seen growing wild or cultivated in the vicinity of Lancaster, Pa.; 1 volume, bound in volume 22, "Pflanzen die ich noch nicht nach dem Linn, bestimen kann, weitl, uftich zu meinem eignen Verbessern beschrieben im Jahr 1788."; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
  - 23. Plantae crytogamicae Lancastriensis, 1795., 1.0 Volume(s); 1 volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 586 M89p.
  - 24. Sammlung von Beiträgen zur Kenntnis der Natur, 1785-1804., 1.0 Volume(s); A collection of notes and articles on natural history, especially that of Pennsylvania; description of Lancaster, Pa.; observations on agriculture; lists of plants and herbs, etc.; 1 volume. "Agricultural journal, 1786" is bound in the same volume.; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
    Old call number 580 M89a.
    - 24a. Agricultural journal, 1786., 1.0 Volume(s) Bound with volume 24, "Sammlung von Beitragen zur Kenntnis der Natur."; Contents similar to Botanisches Tagebuch, 1784-1785: journal and daybook, lists of botanical specimens, meteorological observations, notes of travel, personal and church affairs, etc.; 1 volume, bound in volume 24, "Sammlung von Beiträgen zur Kenntnis der Natur, 1785-1804."; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815 (Volume 1)
  - 25. Letter book, as paymaster of the U.S. Army, May 23, Dec. 3, 1836, 1842; 1.0 Volume(s); 8" x 6 1/2"; Muhlenberg, Peter Gabriel
    Ms. vol. 299p. (see Muhlenberg family papers). FILM 371 FRAME 9.
- Reproductions, 18th and 19th century; 0.25 ln. ft.
  Photostats of letters from, to, and regarding various members of the Muhlenberg family (Frederick Augustus, Henry Augustus, Gotthilf Henry Ernest, Henry Melchior, Peter, and William Augustus). Correspondents include Stephen Elliott, Thomas Jefferson, and George Washington. Also included are reproductions of the diary and notebook of Gotthilf Henry Ernest Muhlenberg.
  - Letters, various correspondents, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, F. A. (Frederick Augustus), 1818-1901
  - Letters to Carey & Hart, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Henry A., (Henry Augustus), 1823-1854
  - Letters, various correspondents, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Henry A., (Henry Augustus), 1823-1854
  - Diary, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Gotthilf Henrich Ernst, 1753-1815
  - Letters to Stephen Elliott, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Gotthilf Henrich Ernst, 1753-1815
  - Letters, various correspondents, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Gotthilf Henrich Ernst, 1753-1815
  - Notebook, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Gotthilf Henrich Ernst, 1753-1815
  - Letters, various correspondents, Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Henry Melchior, 1711-1787
  - Letters, various correspondents, 18th century; Photostats.; Muhlenberg, Peter, 1746-1807